<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration conteyning the iust causes and consyderations of this present warre with the Scottis wherin alsoo appereth  the trewe &amp; right title the Kinges Most Royall Maiesty hath to the souerayntie of Scotlande.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23674623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23674623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1832:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration conteyning the iust causes and consyderations of this present warre with the Scottis wherin alsoo appereth  the trewe &amp; right title the Kinges Most Royall Maiesty hath to the souerayntie of Scotlande.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
                  <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[31] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In officina Thomæ Bertheleti ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. D. XLII [1542]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Henry VIII, 1509-1547.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Kings and rulers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <hi>A DECLA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>RATION, CONTEY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NYNG THE IVST CAVSES</hi> and conſyderations, of this preſent warre with the Scottis, wherin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoo appereth the trewe &amp; right title, that the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges moſt royall maieſty hath to the ſouerayntie of Scotlande.<lb/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>historiated page border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26799:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26799:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EYNG NOVVE</hi> EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to the warre, which we haue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ways hitherto ſo moch abhorred and fled, by our neighbour and Nephieu the kyng of Scottis, one, who, aboue all other, for our manyfold benefites towardis hym, hath moſt iuſt cauſe to loue vs, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor vs, and to reioiſe in our quiet: We haue thought good to notify vnto the world his doinges and beha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour in the prouocation of this warre, and lykewyſe the meanes and wayes by vs vſed to exchue and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde it, and the iuſt and true occaſions, wherby we be nowe prouoked to proſecute the ſame, and by vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and diuulging of that matier, to diſburden ſom part of our inwarde diſpleaſure and griefe, and the circumſtaunces knowen, to lament openly with the worlde, the infelicitie of this tyme, in which thinges of ſuche enormitie do breſt out and appere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THE KYNG</hi> of Scottes our Nephieu and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whom we in his youth &amp; tender age preſerued and maynteined from the great danger of other, and by our authoritie and power conduced hym ſauely to the reall poſſeſſion of his eſtate, He nowe compelleth and forceth vs for preſeruation of our honoure and right, to vſe our puiſſaunce and power agaynſt hym. The like vnkindenes hath ben heretofore ſhewed by other in ſemblable caces againſt goddis lawe, mans lawe, and al humanitie: but the oftener it chaunceth, the more it is to be abhorred, &amp; yet in the perſons of princis for the raritie of theym can ſo happen but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:26799:3"/> as it hath nowe come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IT HATH</hi> ben very rarely and ſeldom ſeen before, that a king of Scottis hath had in mariage a dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of England: We can not, ne wyll not reprehend the kynge our fathers acte therin, but lament and be ſory it toke no better effecte. The kynge our father in that matier mynded loue, amitie, and perpetuall frendſhyp betwene the poſteritie of both, whiche how ſoone it fayled, the death of the kynge of Scottis, as a due punyſhment of god for his iniuſte inuaſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this our realme, is and ſhall be a perpetuall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye to theyr reproche for euer, and yet in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tyme coulde not the vnkyndeneſſe of the father extinguiſhe in vs the naturall loue to our Nephieu his ſonne, being than in the myſerable age of tender youthe: but we than forgettyng the dyſpleaſure that ſhulde haue worthily prouoked vs to inuade that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, nurriſhed and brought vp our Nephieu to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieue his fathers poſſeſſion and gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where in he nowe ſo vnkyndly vſeth and behaueth hym to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, as he compelleth vs to take armour and warre agaynſt hym.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IT IS</hi> ſpecially to be noted, vpon what groundes, and by what meanes we be compelled to this warre, wherin among other is our chiefe griefe and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that vnder a colour of faire ſpech and flattering woordes, we be in dedes ſo iniured contempned and diſpiſed, as we ought not with ſufferaunce to preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte and paſſe ouer. Wordes writinges letters meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, ambaſſiatis, excuſes, allegations, coulde not
<pb facs="tcp:26799:3"/> more pleaſantly, more gently, ne more reuerently be deuiſed and ſente, then hath bene made on the kynge of Scottis behalfe vnto vs, and euer we truſted, the tree wold bryng forth good fruite, that was on thone partie of ſo good a ſtocke, and contynually in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance put forth ſo fayre buddes: and therfore wolde hardely byleue or gyue eare to other, that euer alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the dedes to the contrary, being neuertheleſſe the ſame dedes ſo manyfeſt, as we muſte nedes haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded them, had we not haue ben ſo lothe to thinke euell of our Nephieu, whom we had ſo many wayes bound to be of the beſt ſorte towarde vs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauynge a meſſage ſente vnto vs the yere paſte from our ſayde Nephieu, and a promiſſe made for the repayryng of the ſayd kynge of Scottis vnto vs to Yorke, and after great preparation on our part made therfore, the ſame metyng was not onely diſappoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but alſo at our being at Yorke, in the lieu therof, an inuaſion made by our ſaid Nephieu his ſubiectes into our realme, declaryng an euident contempt and diſpite of vs: We were yet gladde to impute the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute of the metynge to thaduyſe of his counſaylle, and the inuaſion to the lewdnes of his ſubiectes: and according thervnto gaue as benigne and gentyl au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſuche Ambaſſadours, as repayred hither at the Chriſtmas afterwarde, as if noo ſuche cauſes of diſpleaſure had occurred, ſpecially conſyderynge the good woordes, ſwete woordes, pleaſant woordis, eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones proponed by the ſayd Ambaſſadours, not only to excuſe that was paſt, but alſo to perſwade kindnes
<pb facs="tcp:26799:4"/> and perfect amitie to enſue. And albeit the kyng of Scottis hauynge contrary to tharticle of the leage of amitie, receyued and entreteigned ſuche rebelles, as were of the chief and principle, in ſterringe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in the North agaynſt vs, with refuſal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tyme, vpon requeſt made to reſtore the ſame: yet neuertheleſſe vpon offer made by the ſayde ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, to ſende commiſſion to the bordures, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the debates of the confinies in the ſame, with ſo great a pretence of amitie and ſo fayre woordes, as coulde be in ſpeche deſyred: we were contente for the tyme to forbeare to preſſe them ouer extremely in the matier of rebels, Albeit we neuer remitted the ſame, but deſyrous to make triall of our ſayde Nephieu in ſome correſpondence of dedes, condeſcended to the ſendyng of commiſſioners to the borders, whiche to our great charge we dyd, and the kynge of Scottes our ſaid Nephieu the ſemblable. Where after great trauaile made by our Commiſſioners, this fruite en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, that being for our part chalenged a piece of our grounde, playnly vſurped by the Scottis, and of no great value, being alſo for the ſame ſhewed ſuch eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as more ſubſtanciall, more autentique, more playne and euydent, can not be broughte fourthe for any parte of grounde within our realme. The ſame was neuertheleſſe by them denied, refuſed, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence only for this cauſe reiected, that it was made (as they alledged) by Engliſhemen. And yet it was ſoo auncient, as it coulde not be counterfaite nowe, and the value of the grounde ſo lytell, and of ſo ſmal
<pb facs="tcp:26799:4"/> wayte, as no man wolde haue attempted to falſifie for ſuche a matier. And yet this denyall being in this wyſe made vnto our Commiſſioners, they neuer the leſſe by our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement departed as frendes, from the Commiſſioners of Scotlande, takyng order as hath ben accuſtomed for good rule vpon the borders in the meane tyme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AFTER</hi> whyche theyr receſſe, the lorde Maxwell, warden of the weſt marches of Scotland, made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for good rule, but yet added therwith, that the bourderers of Scotlande ſhuld withdrawe their goodes from the bourders of England: And incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentely after the Scottiſſhe men bourdurers, the fourth of Iuly, entred into our realme ſodeynly, and ſpoyled our ſubiectes, contrarye to our leages, euen after ſuche extremitie, as it had bene in tyme of open warre. Wherat we moche meruayled, and were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled therfore to furniſhe our bourdour with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon for defence of the ſame. Whervpon the kyng of Scottis ſente vnto vs Iames Leyrmouth, maiſter of his howſeholde, with letters deuyſed in the moſt pleaſant maner, offerynge redreſſe and reformation of al attemptates. And yet neuertheleſſe at the entre of the ſayde Leyrmouth into England, a great num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of the Scottis, than not loked for, made a forrey into our bourders, to the great annoyance of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, and to theyr extreme detriment, wherwith and with that vnſemely diſſimulation, we were not a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell moued, as reaſon wolde we ſhulde. And yet dyd <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not fynally ſoo extremely perſecute and continue
<pb facs="tcp:26799:5"/> our ſayde diſpleaſure, but that we gaue benigne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſayde Leyrmouth, and ſuffered our ſelfe to be ſomewhat altred by his wordes and fayre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes, tendyng to the perſwaſion that we euer deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to fynde the kynge of Scottis ſuche a Nephieu vnto vs, as our proximitie of bloude, with our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie vnto hym, dyd require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN THE</hi> meane tyme of theſe fayre woordes, the dedes of the borders were as extreme as myghte be, and our ſubiectes ſpoyled: and in a rode made by ſyr Robert Bowes for a reuenge therof, the ſame ſyr Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bowes with many other taken pryſoners, and yet deteyned in Scotlande, without puttynge them to fyne and raunſome, as hath ben euer accuſtomed. And beinge at the ſame tyme a ſurceaunce made on bothe ſydes at the ſuite of the ſayde Leyrmouth for a ſeaſon: the Scottis ceaſſed not to make ſundry inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into our realme in ſuche wyſe, as we were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to forgette fayre wordes, and onelye to conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kyng of Scottes dedes, whiche appered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs of that ſort, as they ought not for our duetie in defence of our ſubiectes, ne coulde not in reſpecte of our honour, he paſſed ouer vnreformed: and therfore put in a redyneſſe our army, as a due meane wherby we myght atteigne ſuche a peace, as for the ſafegard of our ſubiectes we be bounde to procure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AFTER</hi> whiche preparation made, and knowlege had therof, the kyng of Scottis ceſſed not to vſe his accuſtomed meane of fayre wordes, which in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural inclination wrought eftſones their accuſtomed
<pb facs="tcp:26799:5"/> effect, euermore deſirous to fynd in the king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuch a regard and reſpect to be declared in dedes, as the correſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dence of naturall loue in the Nephieu to ſuche an Vncle, as we haue ſhewed our ſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hym, dothe require. Wherfore vpon new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt and ſuite made vnto vs, we determined to ſtay our army at Yorke, appoynting the Duke of Norff. our lieutenaunt, the lorde priuy ſeale, the byſhop of Dureham, and the maſter of our horſes, there to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men treate and conclude with the Ambaſſadours of Scotlande, for an amitie and peax vpon ſuche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as by reaſon and equitie were indyfferent, wherby the warre might be exchued, being by ſundry inuaſion of the Scottis than open and manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN THIS</hi> communication betwene our and their commiſſioners, after diuers degrees of commiſſion, ſhewed by the Scottis, and finally one, that was by our commiſſioners allowed, matiers were proponed for concluſion of amitie, nothing difficile or hard on our part, but ſo agreable to reaſon, as the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Scotlande ſayd, they doubted not, but yf it myght ones be broughte to paſſe, that the kynge of Scottis our Nephieu might haue a meting with vs, all matiers ſhulde eaſyly be componed and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Whervpon they lefte ſpeakynge of any articles of amitie, and the ambaſſadours of Scotland made moche outward ioy in communication of a metinge, they ſhewed them ſelfe in wordis facion and behauor moche to delyte in it, to reioyce in it, and therewith thought it eaſy and facile to be concluded and accom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyſſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:26799:6"/> and for their parte they toke it then for a thing paſſed, a thing concluded, and moſt certayn to take effect, and only deſyred .vi. dayes to obteigne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere from their maiſter, and our army for that tyme to ſtay and go no further. Whervnto our commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners then agreed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AFTER THESE</hi> ſyxe dayes was ſent a commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion out of Scotlande, with power to conclude a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge preciſely at ſuche a place, as they knew wel we wolde not, ne coulde not in wynter obſerue and kepe, wherwith whan our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners were myſcontent, the ambaſſadours of Scotland to relieue that diſple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and to tempre the matier, wherby to winne more tyme, ſhewed forth their inſtructions, wherin liberty was gyuen to the ambaſſadours to excede their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the appoyntment of the place, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any other by our commiſſioners thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, whiche maner of procedyng, when our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners refuſed, alledging that they wold not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a metynge with men, hauynge no commiſſion thervnto, the ambaſſadours of Scotland vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to ſend for a more ample and large commiſſion, agreable to their inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for appoyntment of the place, obteined a delay of other .vi. days, to ſende for the ſaid ample co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion without reſtraynt of place. And after thoſe .vi. dayes they brought forthe a newe commiſſion, made in a good fourme, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. But therwith they ſhewed alſo newe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, conteynynge ſuche a reſtraynte as the former commiſſion dyd conteyne, ſo as the libertie gyuen to
<pb facs="tcp:26799:6"/> the Commiſſioners in the commiſſion was nowe at the laſt remoued and taken away by the inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with addition of a ſpecial charge to the ambaſſadors not to excede the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> thus fyrſte the ambaſſadours of Scotlande ſemed to haue wyll and deſyre to conclude of a place ſemely and conuenient, whiche for want of commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they myght not do, and at the laſte myght haue concluded a metynge by vertue of theyr commiſſion, and then for feare of the commandement in theyr ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond inſtructions they durſt not. And ſo they ſhewed theyr fyrſt inſtructions partly to excuſe theyr kynge, who ſhulde ſeme ſecretely to wyll more, than in the commiſſion he dyd openly profeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND THAN</hi> with an ample commiſſion from the kyng, they ſhewed theyr ſecret inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for defence of them ſelf, why they proceded not according to their commiſſion, not carynge howe muche they charged therin their kyng, whoſe faulte they diſcloſed to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them ſelf, truſting that by benefite of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter approchyng, and the tyme loſt in theyr communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation theyr maiſter ſhulde be defended agaynſte our power for this yere, without doinge for theyr parte that by honour, right, lawe, and leages they be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and bounde to do. And in this meane tyme oure ſubiectes taken priſoners in Scotland coulde not be deliuered vpon any ranſome, contrary to al cuſtome and vſage of the border in the tyme of peax &amp; warre. and in this meane tyme ſtaied a great part of our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my alredy preſted, and in our wages to go forwarde.
<pb facs="tcp:26799:7"/> In this tyme ambaſſadours (as ye haue herde) aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled to talke of an amitie and conclude it not. The treatyng of amitie was put ouer by communication of a metynge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of metyng was ſo handled by alteration of commyſſion and inſtructions on theyr behalfe, as it appereth a playne deuiſe onely excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate for a delay, whyche hath gyuen vs lyght, where vpon more certeinly to iudge the king of Scottis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde affection towardes vs, whoſe dedes and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des well wayed and conſidered, dothe vs playnely to vnderſtande, howe he hath contynually laboured to abuſe vs with ſwete and pleaſant wordes, and to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the appetites of other at home and abrode with his vnkynde and diſpleaſant dedes. In his wordes he profeſſeth an indiſſoluble amitie, he alledgeth kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, he knowlegeth benefites, onely the faulte is that he ſpeaketh an other langage to all the worlde in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and therby ſo toucheth vs in honour and dene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of iuſtyce, as we be inforced and compelled to vſe the ſworde, whiche god hath put in our hande as an extreme remedy, wherby to obteigne bothe quiete for our ſubiectes, &amp; alſo that is due vnto vs by right, pactes, and leages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WE HAVE</hi> paciently ſuffred many deluſions, and notably the laſte yere, when we made preparation at Yorke for his repaire to vs: But ſhuld we ſuffer our people and ſubiectes to be ſo ofte ſpoyled without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy? This is done by the Scottis what ſoo euer theyr wordes be. Shulde we ſuffer our rebelles to be
<pb facs="tcp:26799:7"/> deteyned contrary to the leages without remedye? This is alſo done by them what ſo euer theyr wordes be. Shuld we ſuffer our lande to be vſurped contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our moſt playne euidence, onely vpon a wylle, pryde, and arrogancye of the other partie? This is done by them what ſo euer theyr wordes be. And all theſe be ouer preſumptuouſly done agaynſte vs, and gyue ſuche ſignification of theyr arrogancy, as it is neceſſary for vs to oppreſſe it in the begynning, leſte they ſhuld gather further courage to the greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of vs and our poſteritie hereafter. And yet in the entreatyng of this matier, if we had not eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perceyued the lacke of ſuche affection as prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imitie of bloudde ſhulde require, we wold muche ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue remitted theſe iniuries in reſpecte of proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of bloud to our Nephieu, than we dyd hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the inuaſion of his father. But conſyderyng we be ſo ſurely aſcertayned of the lacke therof, and that our bloud is there frorne with the cold ayre of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, there was neuer prynce more vyolently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to warre then we be, by the vnkynde dealyng, vniuſt behauour, vnprincely demeanour of him that yet in nature is our Nephieu, and in his actes and dedes declareth hym ſelfe not to be moued therwith, ne to haue ſuche erneſt regarde to the obſeruation of his pactes and leages, ne ſuch reſpect to thintreteyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, as naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie byndeth, and conſeruation of amitie dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: whiche we muche lament and be ſory for, and vſe nowe our force and puiſſaunce againſte hym, not
<pb facs="tcp:26799:8"/> for reuengeance of our priuate diſpleaſure (being ſo often deluded as we haue ben) but for recouerye of our right, the preſeruation of our ſubiectes from iniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, and the obſeruation of ſuch leages as haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwene vs, firmely truſting, that almighty god, vnder whom we reigne, woll aſſiſt and ayde our iuſt procedinges herein to the furtherance and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the right, whiche we doubt not ſhal euer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle againſte wronge falſeheade deceipte and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>HITHERTO</hi> it appereth how this preſent warre hath not proceded of any demaund of our right of ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perioritie, which the kinges of Scottes haue alwais knowleged by homage and fealtie to our progeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours euen from the begynnynge: But this warre hath ben prouoked and occaſioned vpon preſent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier of diſpleaſure, preſent iniury, preſent wrong my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by the Nephieu to the Vncle moſt vnnatural<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and ſupported contrary to the deſertes of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites moſt vnkindly. If we had minded the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Scotland, and by the motion of warre to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the ſame, there was neuer kynge of this realme had more oportunity in the minority of our Nephieu Ne in any other realme a prince that hath more iuſte title, more euident title, more certayn title, to any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme that he can clayme, than we haue to Scotland, not diuiſed by pretenſe of mariage, not imagined by couenaunt, or contriued by inuention of argument, but lineally deſcended from the begynnynge of that aſtate eſtabliſhed by our progenitours, and recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:26799:8"/> ſucceſſiuely of the kinges of Scotlande by dedes wordes actes &amp; writinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually almoſt without interruption, or at the leeſt intermiſſion, til the reigne of our progenitour Henry the, VI, in whoſe time the Scottis abuſed the Ciuile warre of this realme, to theyr licence and boldnes, in omitting of their dutie: whiche for the proximitie of bloudde bitwene vs, we haue ben ſlacke to require of them, being alſo of our ſelfe inclined to peace, as we haue euer been alwayes glad, rather without preiudice to omyt to demaunde our right, if it myght conſerue peace, than by deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng therof to be ſene to moue war, ſpecially againſt our neighbour, againſt our Nephieu, agaynſt hym, whom we haue preſerued from daungier, and in ſuch a tyme as it were expedient for all Chriſtendome to be vnite in peace, wherby to be the more able to reſiſt the common ennemy the Turke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BVT</hi> for what ſo euer conſiderations we haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſpeake hitherto of the matier, it is neuer the leſſe true, that the kynges of Scottes haue always knowleged the kynges of Englande ſuperior lordes of the realme of Scotlande, and haue done homage and fealtie for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THIS</hi> appereth fyrſt by hiſtorie, written by ſuch as for confirmation of the trueth in memory, haue truly noted and ſignified the ſame. <hi>SECONDLY</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth by inſtrumentes of homage made by the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Scottis, and dyuers notable perſonages of Scotlande, at dyuers and ſundry times ſealed with theyr ſeales, and remaynynge in our Treaſorye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26799:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THIRDLY</hi> it appereth by regeſters and recordes iudicially and autentiquely made, yet preſerued for confyrmation of the ſame. So as the matier of title being moſt playne, is furniſhed alſo with all maner of euidences for declaration therof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FYRST AS</hi> concernynge hiſtories, whiche be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led witneſſes of tymes, the lyghte of trueth, and the lyfe of memory, and fynally the conuenient way and meane, wherby thinges of antiquitie may be brought to mens knowlege, they ſhewe as playnly this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier as coulde be wyſhed or required, with ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of writers, as coulde not ſo agree vppon an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, conteynyng declaration of ſuch matier as hath moſt euident probabilitie and apparance. For as it is probable and lykely, that for the better adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of iuſtyce amonges rude people, two or mo of one aſtate might be rulers in one countrie vnite as this Iſle is: ſo is it probable and lykely, that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng it was ſo ordred for auoydinge diſcention, that there ſhulde be one ſuperiour in righte, of whom the ſayd aſtates ſhuld depende. According whervnto we rede howe Brutus, of whom the realme than callyd Brytayn toke fyrſt that name (being before that tyme inhabited with gyauntes, people without order or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie) had thre ſonnes, Locrine, Albanact, and Cam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, and determinyng to haue the whole Iſle within the Occean ſea to be after gouerned by them thre, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted Albanact to rule that nowe is called Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Camber the parties of Wales, and Locrine that nowe is called Englande: vnto whom as beinge the
<pb facs="tcp:26799:9"/> elder ſonne, the other two brothers ſhuld do homage recogniſyng and knowleagynge hym as theyr ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. Nowe conſider if Brutus conquered all this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, as the hyſtorye ſayeth he dyd, and then in his owne tyme made this order of ſuperioritie as afore: Howe can there be a title diuiſed of a more playne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge, a more iuſte begynninge, a more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent begynninge for the order of this Ilande, at that tyme ſpecially when the people were rude, which can not without continual ſtrife and variaunce conteyne two or the rulers in all poyntes equall without any maner of ſuperioritie, the inwarde conſcience and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of whiche ſuperioritie ſhulde in ſome part dull and diminiſhe the peruerſe courage of reſiſtence and rebellion. The fyrſt diuiſion of this Iſle we fynde it write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this ſort without cauſe of ſuſpection why they ſhulde wryte amyſſe. And accordynge herevnto we fynde alſo in hyſtory ſet forth by diuerſe, howe for tranſgreſſion againſt this ſuperioritie, our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours haue chaſtiſed the kinges of Scottis, and ſome depoſed, and put other in their places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVE</hi> wil here omyt to ſpeake of the rudenes of the antiquitie in particularitie, which they cared not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit to writing, but ſome authors, as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonius Sabellicus amonges other diligentely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerchynge, what he might truely wryte of al Europe,<note place="margin">Ened 10. Lib. 5.</note> and the Ilandes adioynynge, ouer and beſides that whiche he writeth of the nature maners and condy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Scottis, whiche who ſo lyſt to rede, ſhal fynde to haue bene the very ſame in tymes paſte, that
<pb facs="tcp:26799:10"/> we fynde them nowe at this preſent, he calleth Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande part of Englande, which is agreable to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion aforeſaid, beinge in dede as in the lande con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall without ſeparation of the ſea, ſo alſo by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and fealtie vnite vnto the ſame, as by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar declarations ſhall moſt manifeſtly appere by the teſtimony of ſuche as haue left writing for proue and confirmation therof. In whiche matier paſſing ouer the deathe of kynge Humbre, the actes of Dunwald king of this realme, the diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Belin &amp; Brene, the victories of king Arthure, we ſhal begyn at the yere of our lord, DCCCC, which is, DCXLII, yeres by paſt, a tyme of ſufficient auncientie, from whiche we ſhall make ſpeciall declaration and euidence of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our right and title of ſuperioritie euermore contynued and preſerued hytherto.</p>
            <p>¶<hi>EDVVARDE</hi> the fyrſt before the conqueſt, ſonne to Alured kyng of Englande had vnder his dominion and obedience the king of Scottis. And here is to be noted, that this matier was ſo notorious and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, as Maryon a Scot writing that ſtorye in thoſe dayes, graunteth confeſſeth and teſtifieth the ſame, and this dominion contynued in that ſtate, XXIII, yere: At whyche tyme Athelſtaine ſucceded in the crowne of Englande, and hauynge by battayle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Scotlande, he made one Conſtantine kynge of that partie, to rule and gouerne the countray of Scotlande vnder him, adding this princely woorde, That it was more honour to hym to make a kynge, than to be a kyng.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26799:10"/>
            <p>XXIIII, yeres after that, whiche was the yere of our lorde, DCCCCXLVII, Eldred kynge our progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, Athelſtains brother, toke homage of Iriſe then kinge of Scottis.</p>
            <p>XXX, yeres after that, whiche was the yere of our lorde, DCCCCLXXVII, kyng Edgar our predeceſſor toke homage of Kynalde king of Scottis. Here was a lyttell trouble in Englande by the death of ſayncte Edwarde kynge and martyr, diſtroyed by the deceite of his mother in lawe: but yet within memory.</p>
            <p>XL, yeres after the homage done by Kynald to kyng Edgare, that is to ſay, in the yere of our lord, MXVII, Malcolme the kynge of Scottes dydde homage to Knute our predeceſſour. After this homage done the Scottis vttered ſome piece of theyr naturall diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whervppon by warre made by our progenitour ſainte Edwarde the confeſſour, XXXIX, yere after that homage done, that is to ſay, the yere of our lord, MLVI, Malcolme kynge of Scottis was vanquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the realme of Scotlande gyuen to Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme his ſonne by our ſayd progenitour ſaynte Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: vnto whome the ſayde Malcolme made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and fealtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITHIN, XI,</hi> yeres after that Wylliam Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour entred this realme, wherof he accompted no perfect conqueſt, vntyll he had lykewiſe ſubdued the Scottis, and therfore in the ſayde yere, whiche was in the yere of our lord, MLXVIII, the ſayd Malcolme kynge of Scottis dyd homage to the ſayde William Conquerour, as his ſuperiour by conqueſt kynge of
<pb facs="tcp:26799:11"/> Englande.</p>
            <p>XXV, yeres after that, whiche was the yere of our Lorde, MXCIII, the ſayde Malcolme dyd homage and fealty to William Rufus, ſonne to the ſaid Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Conquerour: and yet after that was for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences and demerites depoſed, and his ſonne ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in his place, who lykewyſe fayled in his duetie, and therfore was ordeyned in that aſtate by the ſayd William Rufus, Edgare brother to the laſte Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme, and ſonne to the fyrſte, who dyd his homage and fealtie accordingely.</p>
            <p>VII, yeres after that, which was in the yere of our lorde, MC, the ſayd Edgar kynge of Scottis, dydde homage to Henry the fyrſte, our progenitour.</p>
            <p>XXXVII, yere after that, Dauid kyng of Scottis did homage to Matilde the Emperatrice, as daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and heyre to Henry the fyrſt. Wherfore beinge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter required by Steuen, then obteynynge poſſeſſion of the realme, to make his homage, he refuſed ſo to do, bycauſe he had before made it to the ſayde Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilde, and thervpon forbare. After whiche Dauids deathe, whiche enſued ſhortely after, the ſonne of the ſayd Dauid made homage to the ſaid kyng Steuen.</p>
            <p>XIIII, yeres after that, whiche was in the yere of our lorde, MCL, William king of Scottis, and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid his brother, with al the nobles of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d made homage to <hi>HENRY</hi> the ſecondes ſonne, with a reſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation of theyr dutie to Henry the ſecond his father.</p>
            <p>XXV, yeres after that, which was in the yere of our lorde, MCLXXV, Wylliam kinge of Scotlande, after
<pb facs="tcp:26799:11"/> moch rebellion and reſiſtence, accordyng to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination, kyng <hi>HENRY</hi> the ſeconde, than being in Normandy, William then kyng of Scottis knowledged fynally his errour, and made his peace and compoſition, confirmed with his great ſeale, and the ſeales of the Nobilitie of Scotlande, makynge therwith his homage and fealtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITHIN, XV,</hi> yeres after that, which was the yere of our lorde, MCLXXXX, the ſayd Wylliam kyng of Scottes, came to our citie of Canturbury, and there dydde homage to our noble progenitour kynge <hi>RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARDE</hi> the fyrſt.</p>
            <p>XIIII, yeres after that, the ſayd William dyd ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to our progenitour kynge <hi>IOHN,</hi> vpon a hyll beſides Lincoln<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, makyng his othe vpon the croſſe of Hubert than archbyſhop of Canturbury, being there preſent a meruaylous multitude aſſembled for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>XXVI, yeres after that, whiche was in the yere of our lorde, MCCXVI, Alexander kyng of Scottis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Margaret, the doughter of oure progenitoure <hi>HENRY</hi> the thyrde, at our citie of Yorke, in the feaſt of Chriſtmas: at which tyme the ſaid Alexander dyd his homage to our ſayde progenitour: who reigned in this realme, LVI, yeres. And therfore betwene the homage made by the ſaide Alexander kyng of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and the homage done by Alexander, ſonne to the ſayd kyng of Scottis, to Edwarde the fyrſt at his coronation at Weſtmeſter, there was about fyfty ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, at whyche tyme the ſayde Alexander kynge of
<pb facs="tcp:26799:12"/> Scottis repaired to the ſayde feaſte of coronation, there dyd his duetie as is afore ſayde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITHIN,</hi> XXVIII, yeres after that, which was the yere of our lorde, MCCLXXXII, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baliol kynge of Scottis, made homage and fealtie to the ſayde kynge Edwarde the fyrſte, our progenitour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AFTER THIS</hi> began Robert Bruſe to vſurpe the crowne of Scotlande, and to moue ſedition therfore, againſte them of the houſe of Ballioll, whiche made for a ſeaſon ſome interruption in the ſayde homage: but yet no intermiſſion without the termes of memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For within, XLIIII, yere after, whiche was the yere of our lorde, MCCCXXVI, Edwarde Baliol, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a great victory in Scotlande agaynſt thother fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and enioyenge the crowne of Scotland, made homage to our progenitour Edwarde the thyrde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND, XX,</hi> yeres after that, which was in the yere of our lorde, MCCCXLVI, Dauid Bruſe, who was euer in the contrary faction, dyd neuertheleſſe in the title of the crowne of Scotland, wherof he was then in poſſeſſion, make homage to our ſayde progenitour Edwarde the thyrde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITHIN,</hi> IX, yeres after, this Edward the thyrde, to chaſtiſe the infidelitie of the Scottis, made warre agaynſt them: where after great victories, Edwarde Balliol hauyng the iuſt and ryght title to the realme of Scotlande, ſurrendred clerely the ſame to our ſaid progenitour at the towne of Rokyſbrough in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande: where our ſaid progenitour accepted the ſame, and than cauſed hym ſelfe to be crowned kynge of
<pb facs="tcp:26799:12"/> Scotlande, and for a tyme enterteigned it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed it, as very proprietarye &amp; owner of the realme, as on thone partie by confiſcation acquyred, and on the other part by free wyll ſurrendred vnto hym.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> then after the death of our ſayd progenitour <hi>EDVVARDE</hi> the thirde, beganne ſeditions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections in this our realme, in the tyme of our pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genitour <hi>RICHARDE</hi> the ſecond, whiche was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the alteration of the ſtate of the ſayd Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde, and the deuolution of the ſame, to Henry the IIII, ſo as the Scottis had ſom leyſure to play their vagues, and folowe their accuſtomed manier. And yet Henry the, V, for recouery of his right in France, commaunded the kyng of Scottis to attende vppon hym in that iourney. And in this tyme the realme of Scotlande being deſcended to the houſe of the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, of which our Nephieu directly cometh, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Stewarde kyng of Scottis, in the yere of our lorde, MCCCCXXIII, made homage to Henry the, VI, at Wyndeſour. Whiche homage was diſtaunt frome the tyme of the other homage made by Dauid Bruſe LX, yeres and more, but farre within the freſſhe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALL</hi> which homages and fealties as they appere by ſtory to haue ben made and done at times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as afore: ſo do there remayne inſtrumentes made thervpon and ſealed with the ſeales of the kynges of Scotlande teſtifyenge the ſame. And yet dothe it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere by ſtory, how the Scottis practiſed to ſteale out of our treaſaury diuers of theſe inſtrumentes, which
<pb facs="tcp:26799:13"/> neuertheleſſe were after recouered agayn. And to the intent ye may knowe of what fourme and tenour the ſayde inſtrumentes be, here is inſerted the effecte in worde and ſentence as they be made, which we do, to mete with the cauellation and contriued euaſion of the Scottes, alleaginge the homage to haue benne made for the Erldome of Huntyngton, whiche is as trewe as the allegation of hym that is burnte in the hande, to ſaye he was cut with a ſikell. And therfore the tenour of the homage is this.</p>
            <p>I Iohn N. kynge of Scottes ſhall be trewe and feythfull vnto you lorde Edward by the grace of god kynge of Englande, the noble and ſuperior lorde of the kyngdome of Scotlande, and vnto you I make my fydelitie of the ſame kyngdome of Scotland, the whiche I holde, and clayme to holde of you: and I ſhall beare to you my feythe and fidelitie of lyfe and lymme and worldely honour agaynſte all men, and feythfully I ſhall knowleage, and ſhal do to you ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice due vnto you of the kyngdome of Scotlande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, as god ſo helpe me &amp; theſe holy euangelies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOVVE FOR</hi> the thyrde parte touchinge recordes and regeſtres, we haue them ſo formall, ſoo autenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, ſo ſeriouſly handeled, and with ſuche circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunces declarynge the matiers, as they be &amp; ought to be a great corroboration of that hath ben in ſtories writen and reported in this matier. For amonges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges we haue the ſolempne acte, and iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al proceſſe of our progenitour <hi>EDVVARD</hi> the firſte, in diſcuſſion of the title of Scotland, when the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:26799:13"/> was challenged by twelue competitiours: That is to ſay,
<list>
                  <item>Florentius comes Holandie.</item>
                  <item>Patricius de Dunbar comes de Merchia.</item>
                  <item>VVillielmus de Veſty.</item>
                  <item>Villielmus de Ros.</item>
                  <item>Robertus de Pinbeny.</item>
                  <item>Nicholaus de Soules.</item>
                  <item>Patricius Galightly.</item>
                  <item>Rogerus de Mundeville.</item>
                  <item>Ioannes Comyn.</item>
                  <item>D. Ioannes de Haſtinges.</item>
                  <item>Ioannes de Balliolo.</item>
                  <item>Robertus de Bruſe.</item>
                  <item>Ercius rex Norvvegie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> fynally after a great conſultation &amp; mature deliberation, with diſcuſſion of the allegatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s propo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned on all parties, ſentence was gyuen for the title of Ballioll, according whervnto he enioyed the realme. But for confirmation of the duety of homage before that tyme obſerued by the kynges of Scottis, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth in thoſe recordes, howe when thoſe competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the realme of Scotland repaired to our ſaid progenitour, as to the chiefe lord for diſcuſſion of the ſame, in as moche as the auctoritie of the iudgement to be gyuen depended thervpon: It was than orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:26799:14"/> that the hole parliament of Scotland ſpirituall temporall and of all degrees aſſembled for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and conſideryng vpon what ground and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation the kynges of Scotlande had in tymes paſte made the ſayd homages and recognition of ſuperyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the ſayd parlyament fynding the ſame ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall good and true, ſhulde if they ſo demed it, yelde and geue place, and by expreſſe conſent recogniſe the ſame. At whiche parlyamente was alledged vnto theym, as appereth in the ſame recordes, not onely theſe actes of the prynces before thoſe dayes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reherſed: but alſo beſydes the teſtimonye of ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, the wrytinges and letters of foreyn princis, at that tyme recitynge and reherſynge the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the ſayde parlyament dyd there agree to this our ſuperioritie, and enſuynge theyr determination dyd particularly and ſeuerally make homage and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aultie with proclamation: That who ſoo euer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drue hym ſelfe from doinge his duetie therin, ſhulde be taken and reputed for a rebel. And ſo all made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage &amp; fealtie to our progenitour Edwarde the firſt. The realme was in the tyme of the diſcuſſion of the title ruled by gardians deputed by him: all caſtels &amp; holdes were ſurrendred to him as to the ſuperior lord in the tyme of vacation, benefices, offices, fees, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions paſſid in that tyme from the mere gift of our ſayde progenitour, as in the right of this crowne of England, Sheriffes named and apoynted, writtis &amp; preceptes made obeyed and executed: And finally al that we do now in the Duchy of Lancaſter, the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:26799:14"/> dyd our progenitour for the tyme of contention for that title in the realme of Scotlande, by the conſent and agrement of all aſtates of the realme aſſembled and conſulted with for that purpoſe. At whiche tyme the byſhoppes of ſaynt Andrewes and Glaſcoo were not as they nowe be archebyſhoppes, but recogniſed the prouince of our archebiſhop of Yorke, whiche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ouer all that countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOVV</hi> if the Scottis wyl take exception to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of theyr pryncis, as made in warre &amp; by force whiche is not true: what wyll they ſay or can they for ſhame alledge agaynſt their owne parlyament, not of ſome, but of all confirmed &amp; teſtified by theyr wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge and ſeales? whervnto nothing enforced them, but right and reaſon, being paſſed in peace and quiet without armour or compulſion. If they ſay they did it not, they ſpeake like them ſelues: If they ſay they dyd it, then doo they nowe lyke them ſelfes, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe their duetie, not ſo moche to be blamed, as to be amended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THVS APPERETH</hi> vnto you the begynnyng of the righte of ſuperioritie, with a perpetuall conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce, without intermiſſion within memory, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne omiſſion and forbearynge vpon the groundes and occaſions before ſpecified we deny not. Wherby they haue many tymes ſought and taken theyr opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, to withdrawe the doinge of theyr duetie in knowlege of our ſuperioritie ouer theym, whiche to auoyde, they haue not cared what they ſayde or alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, though it were neuer ſo vntrue: lyeng alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:26799:15"/> in awayte whan they myght annoy this realme, not without theyr owne great dangier peryl and extreme detriment. But as they detrected the doing of theyr duetie, ſo god euer graunted vnto this realme force to compell them thervnto within memory, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng any theyr interruption by reſiſtence, which vnto the tyme of our progenitour Henry the, VI, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer indured ſo longe as it made intermiſſion within tyme of mynde, wherby the poſſeſſion might ſeme to be enpaired, from the tyme of Henry the, VI, vnto the ſeuenth yere of our reigne, how our realme hath ben for a ſeaſon lacerate and torne by diuerſitie of titles, tyl our time and ſins by warre outwardly vexed and troubled, The ſtory is ſo lamentable for ſome parte therof, as were tediouſe to reherſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SITHENS THE</hi> deathe of our progenitour Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the, VI, our grandfather Edwarde the, IIII, rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, who after great trauailes to atteyne quietnes in his realme, fynally in the tyme of preparation of warre againſt Scotlande, dyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>RICHARDE</hi> the, III, than vſurped for a ſmalle tyme in yeres, whom the kynge oure father by the ſtrength of goddis hande ouerthrewe in battail, and mooſte iuſtly attayned the poſſeſſion of this realme, who neuertheles after the great tempeſtious ſtormes fyndynge all matiers nat yet broughte to a perfecte quiete and reſte, ceaſſed and forbare to require of the Scottis to do theyr duetie, thinkyng it policy rather for that time to aſſay to tame theyr nature by the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant coniunction and conuerſation of affinitie, then
<pb facs="tcp:26799:15"/> to charge them with theyr fault, and require duety of them, when oportunitie ſerued not, by force and feare to conſtrayne and compell them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> thus paſſed ouer the reygne of oure father, without demaunde of this homage. And being our reygne nowe, XXXIIII, yeres, we were, XXI, yere letted by our Nephieu his minority, being then more carefull howe to brynge hym out of daungier, to the place of a king, then to receyue of him homage when he had full poſſeſſion in the ſame. Wherefore beinge now paſſed ſithens the laſt homage made by the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Scottis to oure progenitour Henry the, VI, CXXII, yere, at whiche tyme the homage was done at Wyndeſor by Iames Stuard, then king of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, as afore. LVI of theſe yeres the crowne of this realme was in contention, the trouble wherof engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred alſo ſome buſyneſſe in the tyme of the kyng our father, whiche was, XXIIII, yere: And in our tyme XXI, yere hath paſſed in the minority of our Nephieu So as finally the Scottis reſortynge to their onely defence of diſcontinuance of poſſeſſion, can onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge iuſtly but, XIII, yere of ſylence in the tyme of our reigne, beinge al the other tymes ſythens the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage done by Iames Steward, ſuche as the ſilence in them had they ben neuer ſo longe, coulde nat haue ingendrid preiudice to the loſſe of any right, that may yet be declared and proued due. For what can be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to king Edward for not demanding homage, beinge in ſtrife for that eſtate, whervnto the homage was due? What ſhulde Rycharde the, III. ſerche for
<pb facs="tcp:26799:16"/> homage in Scotlande, that had neither right ne ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to haue homage done vnto hym in Englande? Who can blame our father, knowynge the Scottis nature, neuer to do their duetie but for feare, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded not that of them, whiche they wold exchue if they might, being his realme not clerely than pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from yll ſeede of ſedition, ſparkeled and ſcattered in the cruell ciuile warres before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LAVVE AND</hi> reaſon ſerueth, that the paſſing ouer of tyme not commodious for the purpoſe, is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legable in preſcription for the loſſe of any right. And the minoritie of the kyng of Scottis hath endured XXI, yeres of our reigne, whyche being an impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on their part, the hole preſcription of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, if the matier were preſcriptible, is thus deduced euidentely to, XIII, yere, whiche, XIII, yere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe we haue ceaſſed and forborne to demaunde our duetie, lyke as the Scottis haue lykewyſe ceſſed to offer and tende the ſame. For whiche cauſe neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe we do not enter this warre, ne mynded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde any ſuche matier: Nowe beinge rather deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to reioyſe and take comfort in the frendſhyppe of our Nephieu, as oure neyghbour, than to moue matier vnto hym of diſpleaſure, wherby to alienate ſuche naturall inclination of loue, as he ſhuld haue towarde vs. But ſuch be the workes of god, ſuperior ouer all, to ſuffre occaſions to be minyſtred, whereby due ſuperioritie may be knowen demanded and requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, to the intent that according thervnto all thinges gouerned in due order here, we may to his pleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:26799:16"/> paſſe ouer this lyfe, to his honour and glory, whiche he grant vs to do in ſuch reſt peace and tranquillitie, as ſhalbe mete and conuenient for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="colophon">
            <p>LONDINI in officina Thomae Berthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leti typis impreſſ.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
            <p>ANNO. M.D.XLII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
